A Guide to the Papers of Helen Hunt Jackson, 1840-1885
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Helen Hunt Jackson 1840-1885
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7080-a
29 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited by Clifton Waller Barrett on January 5, 1965, and changed to a gift on July 1, 1991.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 29 items, chiefly correspondence and writings of Helen Hunt Jackson.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series. Series I consists of manuscripts, Series II consists of letters, and Series III consists of a photograph.
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Biographical sketch by Sarah Chauncey Woolsey (pen name, Susan Coolidge) [1885], AMsS, 11p.
  - Poem: "Fra Luigi's Marriage" [1865 Dec 8], AMs, 6p.
  - Poem: "Did the Sky Shut?" n.d., AMsS, 1p.
  - Poem: "November" n.d., AMsS, 1p.
  - Parable: "The Magic Clocks" (Part I) n.d., AMs, 23p.
  - Parable: "The Magic Clocks" (Part II) [1885] Aug 8, AMsS, 24p.
  - Poem: "A Last Prayer" [signature pasted on] n.d., AMS, 2p.
  - Poem: "The Cruise of the Ship Happy" n.d., AMsS, 2p.
  - Poem: "Danger" n.d., AMsS, 1p.
- Series II: Letters
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Josiah Gilbert Holland 1840 Sep 28, ALS, 3p.
    Asks him to help persuade Scribner and Co. to publish her letters and sketches written during a year abroad.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to [Thomas] Niles 1871 Mar 2, ALS, 3p.
    Mentions her review for Scribner's Monthly, suggests he reprint MacDonald's stories with illustrations, calls MacDonald "foremost story teller today."
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to [Alexander Wilson] Drake 1876 Apr 3, ALS, 3p.
    Mentions weather in Colorado and photographs she has received, compliments Drake on his skill as an illustrator.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to [Thomas] Niles 1879 Apr 30, ALS, 2p.
    Asks him to order books of [Thomas Gordon?] Hake for her, states she eagerly awaits his decision on the [Rucherts?] and that the author is very anxious to sell the poem.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Mr. Payne 1880 Dec 28, ALS, 3p.
    Discusses sources of information on Indians and her own book on Indians to be published January 25.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Miss Houghton 1880 Dec 30, ALS, 1p.
    Has received petition from Philadelphia and sends it on with this mail.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to [William Hayes] Ward 1881 May 2, ALS, 2p.
    Asks whether her sonnet on the Shoshone Oath has ever been published in The Independent; she has sent it to Jeannette Leonard Gilder for her paper, The Critic.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Mr. [Henry Oscar?] Houghton [1881] Nov 4, ALS, 4p.
    Wonders why the editor of Fair Newspaper omitted the heading she wrote for the poem, asks if she could be provided a list of all the poems she has written for Atlantic Monthly in the last ten years, wants to publish a volume of sonnets, illustrated, mentions [Thomas] Niles and [John Boyle?] O'Reilly.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Mr. Gardner 1881 Dec 12, ALS, 3p.
    Asks him to get letter promised by Mr. King, which will introduce her to King's friend at Capistrano, mentions her sister, Mrs. Hunt.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Daniel Sharp Ford, in his guise as "Perry Mason" 1882 Jul 30, ALS, 3p.
    Sends five articles for Youth's Companion; also sends photographs to use in illustrating articles; bills him for both.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Henry Chandler Bowen 1883 Sep 23, ALS, 2p.
    Sends a series of papers on Southern California for publication in The Independent and discusses price, asks if he wants a series on Arizona and the Indians of Arizona, mentions Gen. [George] Crook and criticizes proofreader of "Pot of Gold."
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to William Winter 1884 Mar 19, ALS, 2p.
    Compliments Winter on his poem "The Golden Silence," mentions that he has not answered her letters or visited, despite invitation.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Henry Chandler Bowen 1884 Apr 15, ALS, 3p.
    Proposes to write for The Independent a series of papers pertaining to home life, discusses price, mentions St. Nicholas [children's magazine] and William Hayes Ward.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Henry Chandler Bowen 1884 Apr 16, ALS, 2p.
    Defends price she charges for six essays on home life.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Henry Chandler Bowen 1884 Oct 15, ALS, 3p.
    Encloses poem she has written about Indians starving on a reservation while there is an overabundance of wheat in the country, suggest it be published in The Independent, asks who is acting as editor.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Josiah Gilbert Holland n.y. Feb 6, ALS, 2p.
    Expresses sorrow for a misunderstanding, surprised that he thinks she could afford to sell papers on Japan at the same price as ordinary papers, agrees not to tell others.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to [Robert Underwood] Johnson n.y. Mar 15, ALS, 2p.
    Asks for two subscriptions to The World, for herself and Miss Banfield, asks if he would like her to write a notice of Mrs. Dodge's poems for Literary World.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to Moncure D. Conway n.d., ALS, 1p.
    Thanks for sermon, which she returns, having copied it, would like to make copies of the other two of the series.
  - Helen Hunt Jackson to magazine editor n.d., ALS, 2p.
    Part of a longer letter, expresses anger that he published an article she wanted destroyed.
- Series III: Photograph
  - Helen Hunt Jackson n.d., Photograph.
    The Perry Pictures, Boston Editon.